It was April, last year.
في أبريل العام الماضي،
I was on an evening out with friends
كنت أمضي أمسيًة مع أصدقائي
to celebrate one of their birthdays.
لنحتفل فيها بميلاد أحدهم.
We hadn't been all together for a couple of weeks;
لم نجتمع كلنا منذ أسبوعين؛
it was a perfect evening, as we were all reunited.
كانت ليلة رائعة، حيث أننا اجتمعنا كلنا.
At the end of the evening,
في نهاية الليلة،
I caught the last underground train back to the other side of London.
ركبت آخر قطارعائد إلى الجهة الأخرى من لندن.
The journey was smooth.
كانت الرحلة هادئة.
I got back to my local station
عدت إلى محطتي المحلية
and I began the 10-minute walk home.
ثم بدأت المشي لمدة ١٠ دقائق إلى المنزل.
As I turned the corner onto my street,
وبينما كنت متجهة إلى الزاوية المؤدية لشارعي،
my house in sight up ahead,
حيث أرى منزلي هناك،
I heard footsteps behind me
سمعت خطواتٍ خلفي
that seemed to have approached out of nowhere
والتي بدت وكأنها تقترب من العدم
and were picking up pace.
وكانت الخطى تتسارع.
Before I had time to process what was happening,
وقبل أن أملك الوقت لتحليل ما يحصل،
a hand was clapped around my mouth so that I could not breathe,
أطبقت يد على فمي فلم أستطع التنفس،
and the young man behind me dragged me to the ground,
وسحبني ذلك الشاب من خلفي إلى الأرض،
beat my head repeatedly against the pavement
وضرب رأسي عدة مرات على الرصيف
until my face began to bleed,
حتى بدأ وجهي بالنزيف،
kicking me in the back and neck
كان يركلني على ظهري ورقبتي
while he began to assault me,
عندما بدأ بالاعتداء علي،
ripping off my clothes and telling me to "shut up,"
يجردني من ملابسي ويقول لي "اخرسي"،
as I struggled to cry for help.
حيث كنت أصارع لطلب النجدة.
With each smack of my head to the concrete ground,
ومع كل صفعة في رأسي على الإسمنت،
a question echoed through my mind that still haunts me today:
سؤال تردد في ذهني ومازال يلاحقني حتى اليوم:
"Is this going to be how it all ends?"
"هل ستكون هذه نهاية كل شيء؟؟"
Little could I have realized, I'd been followed the whole way
قليلاً كان ما أدركته، لقد كنتُ متبوعةً على طول الطريق
from the moment I left the station.
منذ اللحظة التي غادرت فيها المحطة.
And hours later,
بعد عدة ساعات،
I was standing topless and barelegged in front of the police,
كنتُ أقف عارية الصدر والأقدام أمام الشرطة،
having the cuts and bruises on my naked body photographed
يقومون بتصوير الجروح والكدمات على جسدي العاري
for forensic evidence.
لأجل الأدلة القضائية.
Now, there are few words to describe the all-consuming feelings
الآن، يوجد كلمات قليلة لوصف كل تلك المشاعر
of vulnerability, shame, upset and injustice that I was ridden with
من ضعف، ذلّ، استياء وظلم كلها كانت تملؤني
in that moment and for the weeks to come.
في تلك اللحظة والأسابيع التي تلتها.
But wanting to find a way to condense these feelings
لكن ولأني أردت أن أجد طريقة لتركيز هذه المشاعر
into something ordered that I could work through,
في شكلٍ منظَّم يمكنني التأقلم معه،
I decided to do what felt most natural to me:
قررت أن أفعل ما بدا طبيعياً بالنسبة لي:
I wrote about it.
كتبتُ عن قصتي.
It started out as a cathartic exercise.
انطلقت بها كتمرين مسهِّل.
I wrote a letter to my assaulter,
كتبتُ رسالةً إلى المعتدي علي،
humanizing him as "you,"
واصفةً إياه بكلمة "أنت"،
to identify him as part of the very community
لتعريفه كجزء من المجتمع
that he had so violently abused that night.
الذي أساء إليه بعنف كبير تلك الليلة.
Stressing the tidal-wave effect of his actions,
بالتركيز على تأثير المد والجذر من افعاله
I wrote:
كتبت:
"Did you ever think of the people in your life?
"هل فكرت سابقاً بالأشخاص في حياتك؟
I don't know who the people in your life are.
لا أعرف من هم الأشخاص في حياتك.
I don't know anything about you.
لا أعرف أي شيء عنك.
But I do know this:
لكني أعرفُ ما يلي:
you did not just attack me that night.
أنت لم تهجم عليّ فقط تلك الليلة.
I'm a daughter, I'm a friend,
أنا ابنة، أنا صديقة،
I'm a sister, I'm a pupil,
أنا أخت، أنا طالبة،
I'm a cousin, I'm a niece,
أنا ابنة عم ، ابنة أخت،
I'm a neighbor;
أنا جارة؛
I'm the employee who served everyone coffee
أنا الموظفة التي قدمت القهوة للجميع
in the café under the railway.
في الكافيه تحت الجسر.
And all the people who form these relations to me
وكل أولئك الناس الذين يشكلون تلك العلاقات بالنسبة لي
make up my community.
هم مجتمعي.
And you assaulted every single one of them.
وأنت اعتديت على كل فردٍ منهم.
You violated the truth that I will never cease to fight for,
أنت انتهكت حرمة الحقيقة التي لن أتوقف عن المحاربة لأجلها،
and which all of these people represent:
والتي يمثلها كل أولئك الناس:
that there are infinitely more good people in the world than bad."
والتي تقرّ بوجود الأخيار في العالم أكثر من الأشرار."
But, determined not to let this one incident make me lose faith
لكن بإصراري على ألا أدع هذا الحادث يفقدني إيماني
in the solidarity in my community or humanity as a whole,
بالعزلة في مجتمعي أو الإنسانية ككل،
I recalled the 7/7 terrorist bombings in July 2005 on London transport,
فكرت في ذكرى التفجيرات الإرهابية في تموز 2005 عند محطة لندن للمواصلات،
and how the mayor of London at the time, and indeed my own parents,
وكيف أن عمدة لندن ذلك الحين، وبالطبع أهلي أيضاً،
had insisted that we all get back on the tubes the next day,
كيف أصرّوا على أن نعود جميعنا إلى الأنفاق في اليوم التالي،
so we wouldn't be defined or changed
كي لا يتم كشفنا أو تغييرنا
by those that had made us feel unsafe.
من قبل من جعلنا نشعر بانعدام الأمان.
I told my attacker,
قلتُ لمهاجِمي،
"You've carried out your attack,
أنتَ نفّذت اعتداءك،
but now I'm getting back on my tube.
لكنني الآن أعود إلى نفقي.
My community will not feel we are unsafe walking home after dark.
لن يشعر مجتمعي بأننا غير آمنين عند المشي إلى المنزل في العتمة.
We will get on the last tubes home,
سنعبر آخر الأنفاق نحو المنزل،
and we will walk up our streets alone,
وسنمشي في شوارعنا لوحدنا،
because we will not ingrain or submit to the idea
لأننا لن ننغمس أو نخضع لفكرة
that we are putting ourselves in danger in doing so.
أننا نضع أنفسنا في دائرة الخطر بفعلنا لذلك.
We will continue to come together, like an army,
سنستمر في القدوم معاً، مثل جيش،
when any member of our community is threatened.
في حال تهديد أي فردٍ من مجتمعنا بالخطر.
And this is a fight you will not win."
وهذه معركة لن تربحها."
At the time of writing this letter --
في ذلك الوقت الذي كتبت فيه الرسالة--
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
At the time of writing this letter,
في وقت كتابة هذه الرسالة،
I was studying for my exams in Oxford,
كنت أدرس لامتحاناتي في أوكسفورد،
and I was working on the local student paper there.
وكنت أعمل على تحضير الجريدة الطلابية المحلية هناك.
Despite being lucky enough to have friends and family supporting me,
بغض النظر عن كوني محظوظةً بما يكفي لامتلاكي عائلةً وأصدقاء يدعمونني،
it was an isolating time.
كانت فترةً من العزلة.
I didn't know anyone who'd been through this before;
لم أكن أعرف أي أحدٍ مرّ بهذا الشيء من قبل؛
at least I didn't think I did.
على الأقل لم أكن أظن أني كذلك.
I'd read news reports, statistics, and knew how common sexual assault was,
كنت أقرأ تقارير الأخبار والإحصائيات وعرفت كم كانت الاعتداءات الجنسية شائعة
yet I couldn't actually name a single person
ومع ذلك لم أقدر فعلاً أن أسمي شخصاً واحداً
that I'd heard speak out about an experience of this kind before.
سمعته يتحدث علناً عن تجربة من هذا النوع سابقاً.
So in a somewhat spontaneous decision,
لذا، وبقرارٍ عفويٍّ،
I decided that I would publish my letter in the student paper,
قررت أني سأنشر قصتي في الجريدة الطلابية،
hoping to reach out to others in Oxford
وكلي أملٌ أن تصل للآخرين في أوكسفورد
that might have had a similar experience and be feeling the same way.
الذين قد يكونون خاضعين لتجربة مماثلة ويشعرون بالمثل.
At the end of the letter,
في نهاية الرسالة،
I asked others to write in with their experiences
طلبت من الآخرين أن يكتبوا عن تجاربهم
under the hashtag, "#NotGuilty,"
من خلال هاشتاغ "#لست_مذنباً".
to emphasize that survivors of assault could express themselves
للتأكيد على أن الناجين من الاعتداءات يمكنهم أن يعبروا عن أنفسهم
without feeling shame or guilt about what happened to them --
دون الشعور بالخزي أو الذنب اتجاه ما حصل معهم --
to show that we could all stand up to sexual assault.
لنظهر أننا قادرون على الوقوف في وجه الاعتداءات الجنسية.
What I never anticipated is that almost overnight,
ما لم أكن أتوقعه أبداً أنه تقريباً خلال يوم واحد،
this published letter would go viral.
اصبحت هذه الرسالة حديث المجتمع.
Soon, we were receiving hundreds of stories
أصبحنا نستقبل لاحقاً مئات القصص
from men and women across the world,
من رجال ونساء حول العالم،
which we began to publish on a website I set up.
والتي بدأنا بنشرها على موقع أعددته.
And the hashtag became a campaign.
وتحول الهاشتاغ إلى كلمة #حملة.
There was an Australian mother in her 40s who described how on an evening out,
كان هناك أم أسترالية في الأربعينيات وصفت ما حصل في أمسية،
she was followed to the bathroom
حيث تمت ملاحقتها إلى الحمام
by a man who went to repeatedly grab her crotch.
من قبل رجلٍ ذهب ليمسك فرجها باستمرار.
There was a man in the Netherlands
كان هناك رجل في هولندا
who described how he was date-raped on a visit to London
وصف كيف تم اغتصابه في موعد غرامي في زيارةٍ إلى لندن
and wasn't taken seriously by anyone he reported his case to.
ولم يأخذ أحدٌ قصته بمحمل الجد.
I had personal Facebook messages from people in India and South America,
تلقيت رسائل خاصة على الفيسبوك من أشخاص من الهند وأميريكا الجنوبية،
saying, how can we bring the message of the campaign there?
تقول، كيف يمكننا أن نأتي برسائل الحملة إلى هنا؟
One of the first contributions we had was from a woman called Nikki,
واحدةٌ من أول الاشتراكات التي تلقيناها كانت من امرأة تدعى نيكي،
who described growing up, being molested my her own father.
والتي وصفت حالتها حين كانت تكبر وتتعرض للتحرش من قبل والدها.
And I had friends open up to me
وكان لدي أصدقاء منفتحون لي
about experiences ranging from those that happened last week
برواية تجاربَ تتعدد بين ما حصل في الأسبوع الماضي
to those that happened years ago, that I'd had no idea about.
وما حصل منذ سنوات، والتي لم أكن أعرف شيئاً عنها.
And the more we started to receive these messages,
وكلما بدأنا بتلقي رسائل أكثر،
the more we also started to receive messages of hope --
كلما بدأنا باستقبال رسائل من الأمل --
people feeling empowered by this community of voices
أشخاص يشعرون بالقوة من أصوات هذا المجتمع
standing up to sexual assault and victim-blaming.
يقفون في وجه الاعتداءات الجنسية ولوم الضحية.
One woman called Olivia,
هناك امرأة تدعي أوليفيا،
after describing how she was attacked
بعد وصفها لحالة اعتداءٍ عليها
by someone she had trusted and cared about for a long time,
من قبل شخصٍ وثقت به واهتمت له لزمن طويل،
said, "I've read many of the stories posted here,
قالت: "قرأت الكثير من القصص المنشورة هنا،
and I feel hopeful that if so many women can move forward,
وأشعر بالأمل حيث أنه إذا تحرك الكثير من النساء،
then I can, too.
عندئذ بمقدوري ذلك أيضاً.
I've been inspired by many,
لقد ألهمني الكثيرون،
and I hope I can be as strong as them someday.
وأتمنى أن أكون قويةً مثلهم يوماً ما.
I'm sure I will."
أنا واثقة أني سأكون."
People around the world began tweeting under this hashtag,
بدأ أشخاصٌ حول العالم بنشر التغريدات بهذا الهاشتاغ،
and the letter was republished and covered by the national press,
وتمت إعادة نشر الرسالة وتغطيتها من قبل الصحافة الوطنية،
as well as being translated into several other languages worldwide.
كما تمت ترجمتها إلى لغات عدة حول العالم.
But something struck me about the media attention
لكن شيئاً صدمني حول الانتباه الإعلامي
that this letter was attracting.
بأن هذه الرسالة كانت تجذب الكثير.
For something to be front-page news,
أن يكون شيءٌ كهذا في أخبار الصفحة الرئيسية،
given the word "news" itself,
أن يُعطى وصف "الخبر" بحد ذاته،
we can assume it must be something new or something surprising.
يمكننا أن نفترض أن يكون شيئاً جديداً أو مفاجِئاً.
And yet sexual assault is not something new.
مع ذلك فالاعتداء الجنسي ليس بجديد.
Sexual assault, along with other kinds of injustices,
الاعتداء الجنسي، جنباً إلى جنب مع الأنواع الأخرى من الظلم،
is reported in the media all the time.
تكتب التقارير عنها في الإعلام كل الوقت.
But through the campaign,
لكن من خلال الحملة،
these injustices were framed as not just news stories,
لم يتم تصوير هذا الظلم على أنه فقط قصص إخبارية،
they were firsthand experiences that had affected real people,
لقد كانت خبرات مباشرة أثرت في حياة أشخاص حقيقيين،
who were creating, with the solidarity of others,
الذين كانوا يصنعون بالتضامن مع الآخرين،
what they needed and had previously lacked:
ما كانوا يحتاجونه وما نقصهم في السابق:
a platform to speak out,
منصة للبوح بالحكايا،
the reassurance they weren't alone or to blame for what happened to them
التطمين بأنهم ليسوا وحيدين أو لن يلقى عليهم اللوم على ما حصل معهم
and open discussions that would help to reduce stigma around the issue.
وحوارات مفتوحة بإمكانها أن تساعدهم في تخفيف وصمة العار حول هذه القضية.
The voices of those directly affected were at the forefront of the story --
كانت أصوات هؤلاء المتأثرين مباشرةً في مقدمة القصة --
not the voices of journalists or commentators on social media.
لا أصوات الصحفيين والمعلقين في وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي.
And that's why the story was news.
وهذا ما جعل القصة من الأخبار.
We live in an incredibly interconnected world
نحن نعيش في عالم مترابط بشكل هائل
with the proliferation of social media,
مع تكاثر وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي،
which is of course a fantastic resource for igniting social change.
والتي هي بالطبع مصدر رائع لإشعال فتيل التغيير الاجتماعي.
But it's also made us increasingly reactive,
لكنها جعلتنا أيضاً متفاعلين بشكل متزايد،
from the smallest annoyances of, "Oh, my train's been delayed,"
من أصغر المضايقات مثل "أوه، لقد تأجل موعد القطار،"
to the greatest injustices of war, genocides, terrorist attacks.
إلى أعظم قصص الظلم من الحرب، الإبادة الجماعية والهجمات الإرهابية.
Our default response has become to leap to react to any kind of grievance
أصبح ردنا الطبيعي بأن نهبّ للتفاعل مع أي نوع من الظلم
by tweeting, Facebooking, hastagging --
بالتغريد على تويتر، والفيسبوك، وإطلاق هاشتاغات
anything to show others that we, too, have reacted.
أي شيء لنظهر للآخرين أننا أيضاً قد تفاعلنا.
The problem with reacting in this manner en masse
مشكلة التفاعل بهذه الطريقة ككل
is it can sometimes mean that we don't actually react at all,
أنه قد يعني أحياناً أننا لا نتفاعل بشكل حقيقي مطلقاً،
not in the sense of actually doing anything, anyway.
ليس بقيمة أن نفعل أي شيء حقيقي بكل الأحوال.
It might make ourselves feel better,
يمكنه أن يجعلنا نشعر بحال أفضل،
like we've contributed to a group mourning or outrage,
وكأننا اشتركنا في عزاء مجموعة ما أو غضبها،
but it doesn't actually change anything.
لكنها فعلياً لا تغير من شيء.
And what's more,
وبالأكثر،
it can sometimes drown out the voices
يمكنها أن تُغرق أحياناً أصواتِ من
of those directly affected by the injustice,
هم متأثرون بشكل مباشر بهذا الظلم،
whose needs must be heard.
من يجب لاحتياجاتهم أن تُسمَع.
Worrying, too, is the tendency for some reactions to injustice
القلق أيضاً، هو ميلٌ لبعض التفاعل حول الظلم
to build even more walls,
لبناء المزيد من الجدران،
being quick to point fingers with the hope of providing easy solutions
أن نكون سريعين في توجيه أصابع الاتهام مع الأمل بتقديم حلول سهلة
to complex problems.
لمشكلات معقدة.
One British tabloid, on the publication of my letter,
كتبت صحيفة بريطانية شعبية عن نشر رسالتي،
branded a headline stating,
تصريحاً في عنوان رئيسي،
"Oxford Student Launches Online Campaign to Shame Attacker."
"طالبة في أكسفورد تطلق حملة على الانترنت لفضح المعتدي."
But the campaign never meant to shame anyone.
لكن الحملة لم تكن أبداً لجلب العار لأي أحد.
It meant to let people speak and to make others listen.
كان هدفها أن تجعل الناس تتكلم وتجعل الآخرين يستمعون إليهم.
Divisive Twitter trolls were quick to create even more injustice,
كان هناك تغريدات تقسيمية على التويتر ساخرة تزيد من الظلم،
commenting on my attacker's ethnicity or class
تعطي تعليقاً على عرقية أو صنف من هاجمني
to push their own prejudiced agendas.
ليدفعوا بأجنداتهم المتحيزة.
And some even accused me of feigning the whole thing
حتى أن البعض منهم اتهمني بتلفيق القصة كلها
to push, and I quote,
للدفع بها، وعلّقت لهم،
my "feminist agenda of man-hating."
"إنها أجندتي الأنثوية في كره الرجال."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I know, right?
تماماً، أليس كذلك؟
As if I'm going to be like, "Hey guys! Sorry I can't make it,
وكأنني سأبدو كمن يقول، "يا صحبي، آسفة لا أستطيع فعلها،
I'm busy trying to hate the entire male population
أنا مشغولة بمحاولتي لكره كامل المجتمع الذكوري
by the time I'm 30."
في بلوغي للثلاثين من عمري."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I'm almost sure
الآن، أنا شبه واثقة أن
that these people wouldn't say the things they say in person.
هؤلاء الأشخاص لم يكونوا ليقولوا الأشياء التي قالوها لي شخصياً.
But it's as if because they might be behind a screen,
لكن وكأنه بسبب كونهم خلف الشاشة،
in the comfort in their own home
في راحةٍ مطلقة في بيوتهم على
when on social media,
وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي،
people forget that what they're doing is a public act --
ينسى الناس أن ما يفعلونه هو حدث علني --
that other people will be reading it and be affected by it.
أن الناس الآخرين سيقرؤونه ويتأثرون به.
Returning to my analogy of getting back on our trains,
بالعودة إلى قصتي المشابهة في العودة إلى ركوب القطار،
another main concern I have about this noise that escalates
يهمني شيء أساسي آخر حول هذه الضجة التي تصاعدت
from our online responses to injustice
من ردودنا على الانترنت اتجاه الظلم
is that it can very easily slip into portraying us as the affected party,
هو أنه بإمكانه أن ينزلق بسهولة نحو رسمنا كطرف متأثر،
which can lead to a sense of defeatism,
مما قد يقود لإحساسٍ بالانهزامية،
a kind of mental barrier to seeing any opportunity for positivity or change
كحاجزٍ عقلاني عن رؤية أية فرصة للإيجابية أو التغيير
after a negative situation.
بعد حالةٍ سلبية.
A couple of months before the campaign started
قبل بدء الحملة ببضعة أشهر
or any of this happened to me,
أو قبل أن يحصل أي من هذا معي،
I went to a TEDx event in Oxford,
ذهبت إلى حدث TEDx في أوكسفورد،
and I saw Zelda la Grange speak,
وشاهدت كلمة زيلدا لا غرانغ،
the former private secretary to Nelson Mandela.
السكرتيرة الخاصة السابقة لنيلسون مانديلا.
One of the stories she told really struck me.
صدمتني إحدى القصص التي روتها بشدة،
She spoke of when Mandela was taken to court
روت قصةً عندما سِيق مانديلا إلى المحكمة
by the South African Rugby Union
من قبل اتحاد الرغبي الجنوب أفريقي
after he commissioned an inquiry into sports affairs.
بعد أن أمر بإحداث استجواب في العلاقات الرياضية.
In the courtroom,
في قاعة المحكمة،
he went up to the South African Rugby Union's lawyers,
صعد إلى محاميي اتحاد الرغبي الجنوب أفريقي،
shook them by the hand
صافحهم بيده
and conversed with them, each in their own language.
وتحادث معهم، كل منهم بلغته الخاصة.
And Zelda wanted to protest,
وأرادت زيلدا أن تعترض،
saying they had no right to his respect
قائلةً أنهم لم يستحقوا احترامه أبداً
after this injustice they had caused him.
بعد هذا الظلم الذي سببوه له.
He turned to her and said,
استدار إليها وقال،
"You must never allow the enemy to determine the grounds for battle."
"لا يجب أبداً أن تسمحي للعدو بأن يحدد قواعد المعركة."
At the time of hearing these words,
في اللحظة التي سمعت بها هذه الكلمات
I didn't really know why they were so important,
لم أعرف حقاً ما يجعلها بتلك الأهمية،
but I felt they were, and I wrote them down in a notebook I had on me.
لكني شعرت بأنها كانت مهمة، ودوّنتها في دفترٍ كان معي.
But I've thought about this line a lot ever since.
لكنني فكرت في هذا السطر كثيراً منذ ذاك الحين.
Revenge, or the expression of hatred
الانتقام، أو تعبير الكراهية
towards those who have done us injustice
اتجاه أولئك الذين ارتكبوا المظلُمات
may feel like a human instinct in the face of wrong,
قد يبدو كغريزة بشرية في وجه الخطأ،
but we need to break out of these cycles
لكننا محتاجون لكسر هذه الدورات
if we are to hope to transform negative events of injustice
إن كنا نأمل في تحويل الأحداث السلبية الظالمة
into positive social change.
إلى تغييرات اجتماعية إيجابية.
To do otherwise
نحن بفعل العكس
continues to let the enemy determine the grounds for battle,
نستمر في جعل العدو يحدد قواعد المعركة،
creates a binary,
نخلق ازدواجية،
where we who have suffered become the affected,
حيث نحن الذين عانينا نصبح المتأثرين،
pitted against them, the perpetrators.
مجوفين مقابل مرتكبي الجريمة.
And just like we got back on our tubes,
وبمجرد عودتنا إلى أنفاقنا،
we can't let our platforms for interconnectivity and community
لا يمكننا جعل منصات التواصل والمجتمع
be the places that we settle for defeat.
كأماكن لاستقرارنا بدافع الهزيمة.
But I don't want to discourage a social media response,
لكني لا أريد أن أثبط عزيمة الرد في الوسائط الاجتماعية
because I owe the development of the #NotGuilty campaign
لأني أُدين للتطور الكبير لحملة #لست_مذنباً
almost entirely to social media.
لمواقع التواصل الاجتماعي بالكامل
But I do want to encourage a more considered approach
لكنني أريد حقاً أن أشجع محاولةً أشد اعتباراً
to the way we use it to respond to injustice.
للطريقة التي نستخدمها في الاستجابة للظلم.
The start, I think, is to ask ourselves two things.
علينا أن نبدأ برأيي بسؤال نفسنا سؤالين اثنين.
Firstly: Why do I feel this injustice?
أولاً: لماذا أشعر بهذا الظلم؟
In my case, there were several answers to this.
في حالتي، كان هناك الكثير من الأجوبة لهذا السؤال.
Someone had hurt me and those who I loved,
شخصٌ ما أذاني والأشخاص الذين أحبهم،
under the assumption they wouldn't have to be held to account
على افتراض أنه لم يخضع لمحاسبة
or recognize the damage they had caused.
أو إدراك الضرر الذي سبّبه.
Not only that, but thousands of men and women suffer every day
ليس ذلك فقط، لكن الآلاف من الرجال والنساء يعانون يومياً
from sexual abuse, often in silence,
من الإساءة الجنسية، وغالباً بصمت،
yet it's still a problem we don't give the same airtime to as other issues.
مع ذلك تبقى مشكلةً لا نعطيها حقها في البث كغيرها من القضايا.
It's still an issue many people blame victims for.
ما زالت قضيةً يلوم الناس فيه الضحايا.
Next, ask yourself: How, in recognizing these reasons,
بعد ذلك، اسأل نفسك: كيف، بإدراك هذه الأسباب،
could I go about reversing them?
كيف يمكنني أن أعكسهم؟
With us, this was holding my attacker to account -- and many others.
معنا، كان هذا يضم مهاجمي للحساب -- مع آخرين كثيرين.
It was calling them out on the effect they had caused.
كان يستدعيهم على الأثر الذي سببوه.
It was giving airtime to the issue of sexual assault,
لقد أعطى زمناً جيداً للنقاش في قضية الاعتداء الجنسي،
opening up discussions amongst friends, amongst families, in the media
فاتحاً كل الحوارات وسط الأصدقاء، والعائلات، وفي الإعلام
that had been closed for too long,
والتي كانت منغلقة لزمن طويل،
and stressing that victims shouldn't feel to blame
ومشدداً على أن الضحايا لا يجب أن يُلاموا
for what happened to them.
على ما حصل لهم.
We might still have a long way to go in solving this problem entirely.
ربما ما زلنا نملك طريقاً طويلاً لنسلكه في سبيل حل المشكلة بشكل كامل.
But in this way,
لكن بهذه الطريقة،
we can begin to use social media as an active tool for social justice,
يمكننا البدء باستخدام التواصل الاجتماعي كأداة فعالة للعدل الاجتماعي،
as a tool to educate, to stimulate dialogues,
كأداة للتثقيف، للحث على الحوارات،
to make those in positions of authority aware of an issue
لجعل من في السلطة واعياً لقضية
by listening to those directly affected by it.
بالاستماع إلى من هم متأثرون مباشرةً بها.
Because sometimes these questions don't have easy answers.
لأن هذه الأسئلة لا تملك أحياناً أجوبةً سهلة.
In fact, they rarely do.
في الحقيقة نادراً ما يكون لها جواب.
But this doesn't mean we still can't give them a considered response.
لكن هذا لا يعني أننا ما زلنا غير قادرين على إعطائهم رداً معتبراً.
In situations where you can't go about thinking
في الحالات التي لا يمكنك التفكير فيها
how you'd reverse this feeling of injustice,
كيف ستعكس مشاعر الظلم،
you can still think, maybe not what you can do,
ما زال بإمكانك أن تفكر، ربما ليس بما يمكنك فعله،
but what you can not do.
لكن بما لا يمكن أن تفعله،
You can not build further walls by fighting injustice with more prejudice,
لا يمكنك بناء جدران أبعد عبر محاربة الظلم بالمزيد من التحيز،
more hatred.
المزيد من الكره.
You can not speak over those directly affected by an injustice.
لا يمكنك التحدث عن أولئك المتأثرين بالظلم.
And you can not react to injustice, only to forget about it the next day,
ولا يمكنك أن تتفاعل مع الظلم، لتنساه فقط في اليوم التالي.
just because the rest of Twitter has moved on.
فقط لأن الباقي من التغريدات على تويتر اختفت.
Sometimes not reacting instantly is, ironically,
أحياناً ما يكون عدم التفاعل السريع، بغرابة ،
the best immediate course of action we can take.
هو أفضل طريقة فورية يمكن أن نتخذها في التفاعل.
Because we might be angry, upset and energized by injustice,
لأننا قد نكون غاضبين، حزينين وثائرين بفعل الظلم،
but let's consider our responses.
لكن فلنستوعبْ ردود أفعالنا.
Let us hold people to account, without descending into a culture
دعونا نتمسك بالمحاسبة, بدون الانتماء على جماعة
that thrives off shaming and injustice ourselves.
تُنمّي الإذلال والظلم .
Let us remember that distinction,
فلنتذكّر ذلك التمييز،
so often forgotten by internet users,
المنسي غالباً من مستخدمي الإنترنت،
between criticism and insult.
بين النقد والإهانة.
Let us not forget to think before we speak,
دعونا لا ننسى أن نفكر قبل التحدث،
just because we might have a screen in front of us.
فقط لأننا نملك شاشةً أمامنا.
And when we create noise on social media,
وعندما نخلق الضجيج على التواصل الاجتماعي،
let it not drown out the needs of those affected,
فلنبتعد عن إغراق احتياجات المتأثرين،
but instead let it amplify their voices,
ولنضخم بدلاً عن ذلك أصواتهم،
so the internet becomes a place where you're not the exception
بحيث يصبح الإنترنت مكاناً لا تكون فيه أنت الاستثناء
if you speak out about something that has actually happened to you.
إذا تحدثت عن شيءٍ حصل حقاً معك.
All these considered approaches to injustice
كل تلك المحاولات المعتبرة لإفشاء الظلم
evoke the very keystones on which the internet was built:
تستحضر المحاور التي بُني عليها الإنترنت:
to network, to have signal, to connect --
تكوين شبكة، تكوين إشارة، والاتصال --
all these terms that imply bringing people together,
كل تلك المصطلحات التي تُعنى بربط الناس معاً،
not pushing people apart.
وليس إبعادهم عن بعضهم.
Because if you look up the word "justice" in the dictionary,
لأنك إذا فتشت عن كلمة "عدالة" في القاموس،
before punishment,
قبل المعاقبة،
before administration of law or judicial authority,
قبل مديرية الحقوق أو السلطة التشريعية،
you get:
ستحصل على:
"The maintenance of what is right."
"الحفاظ على ما هو صحيح."
And I think there are few things more "right" in this world
وأظن أن هناك بعض الأشياء أكثر "صحةً" في العالم
than bringing people together,
من ربط الناس معاً،
than unions.
أكثر من الاتحادات.
And if we allow social media to deliver that,
وإذا سمحنا للتواصل الاجتماعي بتوصيل ذلك،
then it can deliver a very powerful form of justice, indeed.
عندئذ يمكنه أن يوصل شكلاً قوياً جداً من العدالة، بكل تأكيد.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)